Finding Aid for Roy C. Vandercook papers, 1900-1957
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Roy C. Vandercook papers 1900-1957
Vandercook, Roy C.
0.3 linear feet and 1 oversize volume
86161 Aa 2; AC
Michigan State Police Commissioner, National Guard Commander and businessman; correspondence, clippings, diary, photographs, and other materials relating to his career.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Roy C. Vandercook (donor no. 3777 )
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Roy C. Vandercook was born in Mason, Michigan on November 20, 1873. Early in his career, he worked as a newspaperman and as a city clerk in Mason (1894). From April 1898 to April 1899, he served as 1st Lieutenant with the 31st Michigan Volunteer Infantry serving in Cuba during the Spanish-American War. After the war, he became a respected Lansing newspaperman. He also continued his involvement with military affairs organizing Michigan's Battery A, First Field Artillery. His service here led to his appointment in 1912 to the Office of Adjutant General of the Michigan National Guard (1912-1915). During World War I, he helped to organize the Michigan State Troops also known as the Michigan State Constabulary. This constabulary would become in 1919 the Michigan State Police. Vandercook served as first Commander of the Michigan State Police (1918-1923). Following this phase of his career, he became manager and lobbyist for the Michigan Railroad Association. He was also vice-chairman of the Ferris Institute Board of Control.
The collection consists of a scattering of correspondence, photographs, and biographical material. Much of the collection is clippings and ephemera. There is, however, a diary for 1920 which includes Vandercook's notes on "red" raids of the 1920's and comment on Governor Alexander J. Groesbeck. Also of interest are some payrolls for Battery A of the First Field Artillery, also an Order Book.
Subjects:
Copper mines and mining--Michigan--Upper Peninsula.; Elections--Michigan--1920.; Ferris, Woodbridge N., 1853-1928.; Groesbeck, Alexander J., 1873-1953.; Michigan. National Guard.; Michigan State Police.; Police, State--Michigan.; Prisons.; Radicalism--Michigan.; Strikes and lockouts--Copper mining--Michigan.; Copper Miners' Strike, Mich., 1913-1914.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Crowds.; Michigan. National Guard.; Military art and science.; Military camps.; Military parades and ceremonies.; Vandercook, Roy C., 1873-
Contributors:
Groesbeck, Alexander J., 1873-1953.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Career materials
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1915-1957 (Box 1)
    (include letter from Alexander J. Groesbeck, January 19, 1922 and Arthur H. Vandenberg, April 12, 1915)
  - Reminiscences (Box 1)
  - Michigan National Guard materials (Box 1)
    (includes payrolls for Battery A of the First Field Artillery, July 11-20, 1910 and August 9-18, 1909 and miscellaneous printed orders and pamphlets)
  - Clippings
    - Jackson Prison Riot, 1912 (Box 1)
    - Ferris Inaugural, 1913-1914 (Box 1)
    - Copper Strike, 1913-1914 (Box 1)
    - Election of 1920 (Box 1)
    - Michigan National Guard and Mexican Border Dispute (Box 1)
    - National Award activities, 2 folders
  - Miscellaneous invitations, cards, programs, clippings, etc. (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1920 (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Order Book, First Battery Field Artillery, June 16, 1905-November 7, 1912 (Volume 1)